<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter sent to Thomas Taylor, Quaker, in the year 1664 in answer to many blasphemous sayings of his in several pieces of paper and in the margent of a book ... / by Lodowick Muggleton.</title>
            <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28839</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10767692</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10767692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1406:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter sent to Thomas Taylor, Quaker, in the year 1664 in answer to many blasphemous sayings of his in several pieces of paper and in the margent of a book ... / by Lodowick Muggleton.</title>
                  <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45752:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER SENT TO THOMAS TAYLOR, Quaker, In the Year 1664.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Anſwer</hi> to many blaſphemous Sayings of his in ſeveral pieces of Paper, and in the Margent of a Book.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many of his wicked ignorant Sayings, I have given an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to ſome of the chief and main things of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, for the Reader to know: The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Heads are ſeven.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> That Chriſt could not make all things of nothing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> That earth and waters were eternal, and out of that matter God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all living creatures.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> That there was a place of reſidence for God to be in, when he created this World.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> How all children are ſaved, though the ſeed of the Serpent, if they die in their childhood.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Of the difference between the fruit of the womb, and the fruits of the fleſh, and how they are two ſeveral trees, and two ſeveral fruits.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> How the Seed of Faith, the Elect Seed, did all fall in <hi>Adam,</hi> and therefore made alive in Chriſt, and how the reprobate ſeed did not fall in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo not made alive in Chriſt; and what it is that purifies the Quakers hearts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> How <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were not capable of any kinde of death before their fall: and how their fall did procure but a temporal death to all the ſeed of <hi>Adam;</hi> but the fall of the ſerpent did procure an eternal death to all his ſeed, who live to men and womens eſtate, and more eſpecially to thoſe that doth deny the perſon and body of Chriſt to be now living in heaven, above the ſtars without a man, as all the Speakers of the Quakers do.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>Lodowick Muggleton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year of our Lord. 1665.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:45752:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45752:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Thomas Taylor,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Underſtand that <hi>Thomas Barnet,</hi> and others that are Well-wiſhers to this Commiſſion of the Spirit, have lent you a Book of our Writings, who are the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, namely, <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton:</hi> I ſuppoſe you have had it ſome time to peruſe, elſe you would not have ſcribled and defaced the Book ſo much as you have, beſides your Papers within the Book; yet nevertheleſs I could have wiſhed thoſe Friends had lent you <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> rather than that, it being the moſt fitteſt Book for Quakers to look into; the other being too heavenly and divine for Quakers to look into. But in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken</hi> I have met with ſuch Antichriſtian ſpirits as you are, who have rayled and blaſphemed againſt the Doctrine of the true God, and the right devil, and the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Spirit, as you have done; neither have I let them go unrewarded for their paines, as you may ſee in that Book: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you go unrewarded for your wicked and hard ſpeeches, raylings, and blaſphemies againſt the Doctrine contained in that Book: for your wickedneſs is ſo much, and your blaſphemies and revilings ſo many, that it would be too tedious to relate, yet for the ſatisfaction of others that ſhall come to ſee this Writing, I ſhall relate ſome of them, and ſpeak a little to a few of the main things of moſt concernment.</p>
            <p>You ſay: <hi>Thy Chriſt that could not make all things of nothing, is a falſe Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Here you have blaſphemed againſt the true Chriſt: for <hi>John Reeve</hi> doth own no other God, or Chriſt, but that Chriſt that was put to death by the Jews, and judged by <hi>Pilate</hi> to be crucified. By him the Worlds were made, but not of nothing: for God never did ſay, neither doth the Scriptures affirm any ſuch thing, that God made the earth and waters of nothing; ſo that you ſhew your ſelf a blaſpheming devil.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We do know and affirm, that earth and waters were eternal, and that darkneſs was over the face of the deep, and in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Spirit of God moved upon the waters; ſo that waters were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45752:3"/>
before the Creation, elſe how could Gods Spirit move upon the face of the deep, had there been no deep waters before? And ſo likewiſe if the earth were not eternal, why is it ſaid by <hi>Moſes, That the earth was without form and void, and darkneſs was over the face of the deep?</hi> The meaning is this, that the earth was in being before God did create it, and darkneſs was upon the face of the deep; ſo that there was deep waters before Gods Spirit did move upon them. And as for the earth being without form and void, the meaning is this, the ſubſtance, being, and matter of the earth it was eternally ſo: but it was void of all form and beauty, not fit for any of Gods creatures to live in it, until God in the beginning created it: For when Gods Spirit moved upon the waters, the meaning is this, he commanded the waters to be gathered into one place, and the dry land did appear. So likewiſe God made two great Lights, <hi>the one to rule the day, and the other to rule the night:</hi> that is, the Sun ſhould rule and govern the earth, and give life to the herbs, and trees, and fruits of the earth, and the Moon ſhould give life to the waters, and rule them: And in this manner God created the earth, and the waters; but all this while God had matter to make theſe things of, for earth and waters were before.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He did not make the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and the hoſt of heaven of nothing; for of nothing comes nothing, though you ſay <hi>it is an heatheniſh ſaying:</hi> let it be the ſaying of a heathen man, it is a true ſaying a ſaying that no Prophet, nor Apoſtle doth deny: none but ſuch Antichriſtian devils as you Quakers are, that will have God to make all things of nothing, elſe you wil call him a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as you have done in your Writings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Furthermore, where do you blinde Quakers think this vaſte earth and waters were before God created them, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Moſes</hi> relation, is not ſix thouſand years? and we can know nothing of the Creation of the world, but it muſt be grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Moſes</hi> his words: I ſay, where do you think theſe great ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of earth and waters were before? Certainly you Quakers do believe that they came out of Gods belly; for your God is ſo big a God, that he can fill heaven and earth, and all places, and be in every Quakers body, and make all things of nothing beſides.</p>
            <p>So that the Quakers God is ſo big, that he cannot be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, yet they get him within them, and when they die, then he gets them into him again.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45752:3"/>So the Quakers God and their Souls gets one into another, ſo that no body elſe can tell where to finde either of them both. But my God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who is a diſtinct perſon in form of a man, by whom the Worlds were framed, he will finde you out when your ſouls are rotted in the duſt of the earth, think of your ſelf what you will, it will be as I have ſaid.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if earth and waters were made of nothing, then I ſay they ſhall turn to nothing again: and if your God did ſpeak them out of his own bulk or belly, as aforeſaid, then I ſay, he will ſpeak them into his belly again, ſo that no man need to fear dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; for all that came out of God ſhall go into him again, and if they were made of nothing, they ſhall turn to nothing again. I ſpeak theſe things, that whoſoever ſhall read this Writing, may ſee the vanity of the Quakers doctrine, and be aſhamed of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>John Reeve</hi> doth ſay, <hi>That God muſt have ſome place of reſidence when he created this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your anſwer to this, you flap your hand in the mouth, and ſay, <hi>God abides in himſelf, and is what he is.</hi> And further you ſay, <hi>To cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate is moſt properly to bring ſomething out of nothing by the powerful word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I marvel what ſatisfaction any man can have in his minde in believing in a Quakers God, to tell a man that God abides in himſelf, and is what he is, but never tells what he is, nor whether he be any glorious ſubſtance, or form, or whether he have any nature; which to know God in his form and nature, is life eternal.</p>
            <p>But to ſay a thing abides in it ſelf, and is of its ſelf, and not to tell what that is that abides in its ſelf, it is Riddle me, Riddle me, what is this? But it is like all the reſt of the Quakers points of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; for they are miſtaken in every true point of doctrine, which are but ſix.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the form and nature of the true God. 2. The form and nature of the right devil. 3. The place and nature of heaven. 4. The place and nature of hell. 5. The mortality of the Soul. 6. The perſons and natures of Angels. Theſe ſix Principles are the ground of all true knowledge, in relation to eternal life; but the Quakers doctrine is ignorant of every one of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are groſly miſtaken in their God, both in his form and nature: for they ſay he is ſo big that no place, neither heaven nor earth can contain him: when as the Scriptures ſaith, <hi>he made man
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45752:4"/>
in his own image and likeneſs,</hi> and he calls himſelf a man: for when the man ſaid to Chriſt, when on earth, <hi>Good maſter, what ſhall I do to inherit eternal life?</hi> Chriſt anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Why calleſt thou me good? there is no man good but one, even God;</hi> So that Chriſt did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God to be a man, for he was God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Quakers are as much miſtaken in the right devil, for they know not how the devil came to be, nor what will become of him hereafter, though many of them their own ſouls is the devil.</p>
            <p>And ſo of Heaven, and of hell, they are ignorant of any places where they are; for they know no other places of glory nor pain, but what is within them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They have got no mortal Souls that can die.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as for perſons and natures of Angels, they know not what I mean by it; ſo that God and devil, hell and Heaven, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls and Angels, are all within them, and when they die, they deliver up all this within them, it goes into God again, and ſo are no more ſenſible of joy nor ſorrow, than they were before they had a being.</p>
            <p>For I perceive by this <hi>Thomas Taylor,</hi> that the Speakers of the Quakers go all in one ſtrain, onely ſome of them are more ſubtile than others, to hide themſelves with the words of the Scriptures, carrying the ſenſe of the Scriptures in an Allegory, and ſo gets Chriſt within them, and ſo keeps his body from going up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above the ſtars: But that Chriſt in a body above the ſtars, hath given me power that am but a mortal man, over that Chriſt within you, and that you ſhall know to your eternal pain and ſhame.</p>
            <p>Furthermore you ſay, <hi>To create is moſt properly to bring ſomething out of nothing, by the powerful word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 In this you ſhew your ſelf to be one of the ſerpents ſeed indeed; for that was the Serpent-angel his ſin in heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſtars, which you ſo much ſlight: I ſay, it was his ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was thrown down from heaven; for be thought in himſelf if he had been God, he would have made all things of nothing, he would have created all living creatures without ſubſtance or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is to ſay, of nothing: This was the Serpents ſin and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when he was in the ſtate of immortality and glory.</p>
            <p>And you being of his ſeed, you ſhall ſpeak and act the ſame ſin in the ſtate of mortality and ſhame; which is a clear teſtimony to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45752:4"/>
me that you are of the Serpents ſeed: for you will have God to do that which he cannot do, to make earth and waters, and all other things of nothing, elſe you call him a devil, or a falſe God. For I muſt tell you, that God never ſaid ſo himſelf that he would, or could make living or dead ſubſtances of nothing; neither did any Prophet, or Apoſtle, or Saint, believe any ſuch thing; but it was always the devils nature to look upon Gods power to be greater than it is, or elſe to be leſs than it is: for the devil is always mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in Gods Infiniteneſs; but the Seed of Faith knoweth by faith what Gods power is, ſo far as to the ſaving of the ſoul, to wit, that God did make living creatures of dead ſenſleſs matter; and living forms of formleſs ſubſtance, and that God could, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d did die, and that he can, and will raiſe the ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs, and the ſeed of the ſerpent, you being one, to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs miſery, though both Seeds be aſleep in the duſt of the earth, until the day appointed.</p>
            <p>This is true faith in Gods power, and that which <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, and us the Witneſſes of the Spirit did, and doth witneſs unto, againſt all the ſeed of the ſerpent whatſoever; for though by faith we underſtand the World was made, yet by faith we underſtand, and ſo did the Apoſtles, that the World was not made of nothing, but by the word of Gods power it was made of ſomething, to wit, of earth, and waters which were eternal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You call theſe wicked ſayings, becauſe we ſay, <hi>no children dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though they be the ſeed of the ſerpent, if they die in their childhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this you ſay, <hi>That the ſerpent was curſed from the beginning for,</hi> ſay you, <hi>certainly all his ſeed, young and old muſt be ſo; for,</hi> ſay you, <hi>as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the tree, ſo are its fruits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Here you that have any light of Faith in you, may ſee the groſs darkneſs of this man; for he cannot abide ſuch a God that hath not power to make things of nothing, and now he is angry becauſe God doth not damn children, if they be of the ſeed of the ſerpent, for he is angry with <hi>John Reeve</hi> for ſaying all chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren will find mercy, as aforeſaid; for, ſaith he, <hi>all young, and old muſt be damned of the ſerpents ſeed:</hi> and this is his ground, <hi>as is the tree ſo are its fruits.</hi> This man would have God to do that which he cannot do, as I ſaid before; ſo he would have God to be more cruel then he is, to condemn children who have done neither good nor evil, which the Scriptures doth no wayes juſtifie: for though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45752:5"/>
God doth ſay, <hi>He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy; Jacob have I loved, but Eſau have I hated, before they had done good or evil:</hi> And that ſaying, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the ſerpents head:</hi> And of that ſaying, <hi>The election of God ſtands ſure.</hi> All theſe places of Scriptures doth not reach that children ſhould be damned, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſeed of the ſerpent is.</p>
            <p>For this is to be minded, that the Scriptures were ſpoken to men and women capable of underſtanding, for God did not ſay to children, <hi>I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy,</hi> it was to men that underſtood what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid: Likewiſe the Apoſtles ſpake to men and women, and not to children, elſe why ſhould the Apoſtles exhort the people <hi>to make their calling and election ſure?</hi> It would have been a vain thing to give exhortation to children. And as for <hi>the ſeed of the woman bruiſing the head of the ſerpent,</hi> it is in relation to men and women: for doth not men and women that are the ſeed of the woman, who have faith in their hearts, by their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſufferings, break or bruiſe the head of the ſerpentine men and women, who are the ſeed of the ſerpent, who doth rage, and rail, and perſecute the innocent? ſo that children have nothing to do in this matter.</p>
            <p>And as for that ſaying of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau, the one being loved of God, and the other hated, when they were both in the womb:</hi> To that I ſay, though <hi>Jacob</hi> was in Gods decree beloved, and <hi>Eſau</hi> in Gods decree hated, or reprobated, yet this I ſay, they were decreed and appointed to live to mans eſtate, ſo that they might both be capable of election and reprobation, and not to die in their childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. And this I ſay further, that if you <hi>T. T.</hi> had died in your childehood, you ſhould have been ſaved, though I know you are of the ſeed of the ſerpent, but you being appointed to be damned to eternity, you were appointed to live to deſpiſe the living God, and blaſpheme againſt the Doctrine of the true God, declared by thoſe Meſſengers whom he hath ſent.</p>
            <p>And as for that ſaying of yours, <hi>As the tree is ſo is the fruit:</hi> Your meaning is, if the ſerpent be damned, the children that are his ſeed muſt be damned alſo. Here you ſhew your groſs darkneſs and ignorance in the Scriptures, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>A good tree bringeth forth good fruit, and an evil tree bringeth forth evil fruit,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you conclude that children are fruits of the ſerpent, he being that evil tree.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45752:5"/>
            <p n="5">5. To this I anſwer: That the meaning of the Scriptures in thoſe words aforeſaid, is not meant that children that are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and born, I ſay, they are not counted the fruits of the ſerpent: for we ſee by experience, and by the Scriptures, that ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate men and women, who are both of the ſeed of the ſerpent, yet the childe that is begotten by them, is of the elect; this I know by experience ſince I came to know the Scriptures, and could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between the two Seeds.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe it is clear by Scripture, that a faithful man and woman, they being both of them the Seed of Faith, that is, the Seed of the Woman; for there is but two Seeds ſpoken of in Scripture, that hath begotten reprobates, as that of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca,</hi> they being both of the elect Seed, yet they begot <hi>Eſau,</hi> which the Scriptures brands for a Reprobate: So that ſometimes two reprobates may get an elect childe, one or more; and two of the faithful ſeed may beget one, or more reprobates: ſo that children are not called in the Scriptures fruits of the Serpent tree; for children are trees themſelves, if they live to maturity of age.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thoſe motions and actions which theſe trees bring forth in their lives and converſations, are called in Scripture fruits of the tree: if good motions and actions, then called a good tree: if evil and ſinful motions, then called an evil, or corrupt tree: for the good tree bringeth forth good fruit, even the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is patience, meekneſs, love, and faith in God, and ſuch like fruits, which good trees, which are men and women, do bring forth. So likewiſe the evil tree is men and women alſo, and they bring forth evil fruits, even the fruits of the fleſh, which is envy, unbelief, perſecution, blaſphemy againſt the true God; theſe and ſuch like fruits proceed from the evil tree of the reaſon in man, and the good fruits proceed from the good tree, which is the faith in man: for there is but two trees ſpoken of in Scriptures, to wit, the Tree of Life, ſignifying the Tree of Faith; and the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, ſignifying the tree of reaſon: ſo that all men, good and bad, are ranked under theſe two trees, and thoſe men that bring forth fruits of Faith, as aforeſaid, may be ſaid to bring forth good fruit: and thoſe men that bring forth fruits of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as aforeſaid, may be ſaid to bring forth evil fruit, as you have done: So that what fruits man or woman bringeth forth in their life, being come to age, is counted by the Scriptures good or evil
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45752:6"/>
fruit, and ſo ſaid to proceed from a good tree, or an evil tree, and not with any relation to the fruit of the womb that is generated and begotten as children. Therefore when <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>The axis laid to the root of the tree</hi> he meant wiſe and prudent men who were wicked perſecutors: he did not mean that their yong children ſhould be hewen down and caſt into the fire.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe when the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the fruits of the Spirit, and the fruits of the fleſh, he tells what they both are, ſo that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not called the fruits of the ſerpent-tree, though they be of the ſame ſeed: for ſeed is one thing, and fruit is another, ſo you erre, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God; for I never knew any Quaker give any Interpretation of Scripture, but ſpeaks the words as they lye, which is the cauſe of their groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake of the meaning of the Scriptures, and run into thoſe and ſuch like errors that God fills heaven and earth; from theſe words they believe God is ſo big as to fill heaven and earth. And of that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Know you not that Chriſt is in you, except you be reprobates?</hi> From theſe words they ground their faith that Chriſt is within them, and ſo will admit of no body, or perſon of Chriſt without them, nor in heaven above the ſtars, and ſo of other ſayings in Scripture: As that, <hi>that Chriſt enlightneth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> but will admit of no interpretation themſelves, becauſe they cannot; but are angry with others that can: for the Scriptures being truly interpreted, diſcovereth the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles to be the greateſt cheat and deceit, and more Antichriſtian than the Pope, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sect whatſoever in matter of Religion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You do upbraid <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, becauſe we are in the fallen ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> but you <hi>Quakers</hi> do not acknowledge your ſelves in that fallen ſtate: you are not willing to be found in that ſtate, for you look upon your ſelves ſo purifi'd by the light of Chriſt within you, that you are become perfect in your own conceit; but you know not what that perfection is the Scriptures ſpeak of? for I am your ſure hearts are not purified by faith. How can your hearts be purified by faith, when as your faith hath never an object? for your God, nor Chriſt, hath never a body nor perſon of his own, but he muſt be beholding to every <hi>Quakers</hi> body to reſide in, and he is every where beſides; therefore what faith can you have to purifie your hearts, when as no God can be found but what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you? But I ſhall ſhew what it is that purifies your hearts, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45752:6"/>
what ſins you are cleanſed from: that which purifies your hearts, is the Law written in your ſeed and nature, even the ſame as was written in the Angel-ſerpents nature before his fall, which is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the nature of reaſon: So the Angels nature being in you, and the Moral Law being written in it, it hath the ſame workings in you, as the heathens had the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, to wit, your thoughts accuſing and excuſing, and the motions of this Law ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in your minds, you call <hi>the light of Chriſt,</hi> when indeed it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the light of the Law: for if it were the light of Chriſt, it would make you to own the perſon and body of Chriſt without you, as well as to own Chriſt within you; and if you <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhould do ſo, your Principles would quickly fall. And as for the ſins your hearts are cleanſed from, they are no other but ſuch like as theſe, that is to ſay, to keep the Hat on the Head before a Magiſtrate, and to finde f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lt with Gold-lace, and a piece of Ribbin, a Band-ſtring, and a gold Button, and to rend and tear Gold-lace, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lace off their Clothes, and burn it, and to uſe the language of <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou.</hi> He or ſhe that gets <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> perfectly, is a very good <hi>Quaker,</hi> they are gotten half way to the <hi>Quakers</hi> heaven. Theſe, and ſuch like righteouſneſs, is the <hi>Quakers</hi> perfection, and all the cleanſing of heart they have: this I know to be true, for I know they have no faith to purifie their hearts, neither can they be juſtified by faith, and have peace with God. For how can they have peace with God, when as they own no other God in a body but what is within them, but they will finde that God within them to be the greateſt tormenting devil of all.</p>
            <p>Again, I marvel how you <hi>Quakers</hi> came to make it ſuch a great ſin for a man put off his Hat to a Magiſtrate! I do not remember any place of Scripture, that it was the practice of Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or Saints. Surely your Teachers might have given their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples a little more liberty than they have: for you <hi>Quakers</hi> do not read that the Prophets, when they went with Meſſages from God to the Kings and Rulers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I ſay, we do not read they went before the Chief Magiſtrates with their hats on their heads Likewiſe the Apoſtles, when they were brought before the Rulers of the Jewes, we do not read they went with their hats on their heads. Are you <hi>Quakers</hi> certain that <hi>Paul</hi> had his hat on his head when he ſpake for himſelf before King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and Noble <hi>Feſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſitting in the Judgement ſeat? Neither did <hi>Paul</hi> uſe the word <hi>thee</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45752:7"/>
and <hi>thou</hi> altogether to them, but gave them civil reſpect, titles of Honor, one <hi>Noble Feſtus,</hi> and the other <hi>Oh King Agrippa,</hi> according to the places of honor they had in this world. So that the Apoſtles did not tye the Believers of them to the hat on, and to <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> Magiſtrates, as you Speakers of the <hi>Quakers</hi> do. Beſides, if it could be proved, that Prophets and Apoſtles did keep the hat on, and <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> Magiſtrates, yet would it be no ground for you <hi>Quakers</hi> to do ſo: for God never choſe, nor ſent you, as he did them. God never beſtowed ſo much honor upon any of you to make you Meſſengers to Kings or Magiſtrates, for you are but private men not choſen of God, as all true Prophets, Apoſtles, and we the Witneſſes of the Spirit were; yet you by the light within you, will imitate thoſe that are choſen by voice of words from a God without us; nay, you are more impudent in your way, than ever any Prophet or Apoſtle was who were choſen of God, and made equal with Kings in power from on high, yet have given ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil reſpect unto Kings and Magiſtrates, they being as Gods on this earth, as the Scripture ſaith. But ſeeing the hat put off to a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is ſuch a great ſin to a <hi>Quaker,</hi> I ſhall let him alone in his righteouſneſs, and let him ſee if that righteouſneſs will deliver him in the day of trouble.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken ſomething more of the hat than I thought to do, onely to inform thoſe that ſhall ſee it, that the Scriptures doth no ways juſtifie ſuch a practice, but it is one of the <hi>Quakers</hi> main points of doctrine they hold forth, and if that and ſuch like things will not ſave them, they muſt be damned; for their righteouſneſs is as much in the hat, as in the heart: for I am ſure they have no true faith in their hearts, nor in the true perſonal God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in glory, in heaven above the ſtars.</p>
            <p>And as for us being in the fallen ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> I do acknowledge and confeſs it, therefore we are redeemed by Chriſts death: for all that are in the fallen ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> are made alive by Chriſt, and all that are not found in the fallen ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> will certainly be damned to eternity: for they that did not fall in <hi>Adam,</hi> did fall in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Angel, and ſo have no benefit in Chriſts death, becauſe that Chriſt took not on him the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> was the ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> in the fallen ſtate, and Chriſt redeemed him by his death, and all his ſeed: I mean by his death without me, and not of his death within me, as the <hi>Quakers</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45752:7"/>
do vainly imagine: for they own no other death of Chriſt, but what is within them, what ever they pretend by uſing the words of the Scripture, becauſe they ſo frequently ſpeak of Chriſts death, but they own no other death of Chriſt, nor benefit by it but what they have within them: reſurrection is all within them.</p>
            <p>I marvel why you <hi>Quakers</hi> ſhould talk of Chriſt loving his Church, and that by one ſuffering Chriſt hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, when as yo own no body of Chriſt without you, but it is becauſe you read ſuch words in the Scriptures, which were other mens words, and faith: alas, what benefit will that be to you to aſſume to your ſelf that which did belong to others! for what is that you what the Apoſtles ſaid to thoſe Believers at that time? they underſtood what the Apoſtles meant by thoſe ſayings; for the Scriptures were not ſpoken to <hi>Quakers,</hi> nor given to them, neither do you underſtand them: the Scriptures were given to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, neither doth any man underſtand them, or can truly interpret them but us two onely, we being the choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit: for we onely can unfold what that Fountain is which is open for ſin, and for uncleanneſs; for every Commiſſionated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath the Key of <hi>David</hi> given unto him to open the hidden my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, even the fountain of living Water, to wit, the knowledge of the true God, and the right devil, with many other heavenly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets hinted at in the Scriptures; which to know is as a Fountain of Water of Life, to thoſe that underſtand them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We do confeſs that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were not capable of any kinde of death, until they were both defiled with the ſinful nature of the Angelical ſerpent.</p>
            <p>To which, this <hi>T. T.</hi> ſaith, <hi>To the glory of truth, that ſeeing Chriſt came to reſtore us that which</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>loſt, with advantage, it muſt needs follow that the true Believers who are become, even now, whileſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, freed from all kinde of death, and ſo are not capable of any death in their ſouls, no more than</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>was in their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, becauſe the Scripture ſaith,</hi> that he that believes in Chriſt is paſſed from death unto life, <hi>and ſuch as abides in that faith ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver die, but the Spirit of Life is in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here this man ſhews his groſs darkneſs and ignorance of the ſpiritual meaning of the Scriptures: for obſerve what is ſaid before, that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> had no kinde of death in them before their fall, yet this let the Reader minde, that the death they did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45752:8"/>
procure by their fall, it was but a temporal death, and that death God threatned them with, it was but temporal, though the fear of eternal death might be in them by reaſon of the fall; but the death it ſelf which God threatned upon them, was but a natural death, neither did God take off, or free them from it: for <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did die, yet they had the promiſe of Chriſt made ſure to them more than any. <hi>Quaker</hi> ever had: And yet this promiſe of Chriſt <hi>to bruiſe the ſerpents head,</hi> it did not free <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> from this firſt death, but it freed them from the fear of the ſecond death, and from the ſecond death it ſelf, even that eternal death. But as for a natural death, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, and Chriſt himſelf taſted death: for this firſt death enters upon all, both man and beaſt, but the ſecond death which is eternal, it enters upon none but upon the ſerpent and his ſeed: and this eternal death is that which they, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and their ſeed, are delivered from, by believing in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And thus we that are found in the fallen ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by Chriſt, that is, we are reſtored to a better and a more glorious ſtate and condition than that of <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency. But you <hi>Quakers</hi> do expect no higher ſalvation than that of <hi>Adam,</hi> but you will not paſs thorow death to it, but you will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it a more eaſie way: For you ſay, <hi>it muſt needs follow that the true Believers who are become even now, whileſt upon the earth, freed from all kinde of death, and ſo are not capable of any death in their ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, that Chriſt never ſaid that he would free man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde from a natural death, nor reſtore man to the ſtate that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was in, but he came to ſave mankinde from eternal death; therefore he ſaith, <hi>He that believeth in me ſhall never die.</hi> And of that ſaying, <hi>he is paſſed from death to life,</hi> that is, he ſhall never die a ſpiritual and eternal death; for he is paſſed from the fear of this firſt death, to the aſſurance of eternal life: for aſſurance in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is many times taken for the thing it ſelf: but Chriſt never freed his Diſciples from a temporal death, notwithſtanding they had eternal life abiding in them. And that Apoſtle who ſaid, <hi>We are paſſed from death to life,</hi> did die a natural death himſelf, and ſo did the Prophets of old, as in the <hi>Acts</hi> it is ſaid by <hi>Peter</hi> to the Jews, <hi>Which of the Prophets have not your fathers perſecuted, and have ſlain, which ſhewed of the coming of the Juſt One?</hi> And was not <hi>Steven</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, a man full of the holy Ghoſt? yet his ſoul was put
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45752:8"/>
to death, and <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, and thoſe that believed their doctrine, did not they die, or elſe were put to death? yet theſe were all paſſed from death to life, yet they all died a natural death, or was put to death: for it cannot properly be ſaid to die, if the ſoul ſlips out of the body, and leaves the body behinde, as you <hi>Quakers,</hi> and many others do vainly imagine; ſo that your ignorance in the ſpiritual meaning of the Scriptures, is bewrayed; for you <hi>Quakers</hi> are the darkeſt pieces to interpret Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, of any other Opinions in the world, for you will name places of Scriptures, but never interpret any, that makes all the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſo dark; for ask them a queſtion in Scripture, they will give you no anſwer, but perhaps bid them minde the light within them: or elſe ſay, it is the fleſh that asks, or ſuch like ſayings, ſo they baffle and trouble ignorant people which knoweth not their Principles, nor the meaning of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>I thought good to anſwer theſe few particulars, they being of ſome concernment for thoſe to know, who are not well grounded in the Doctrine contained in thoſe Books you ſo much villifie and ſpeak evil of: for I would have others to ſee this Writing as well as your ſelf; for you Speakers of the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſeldom let any of your believers ſee my Writings, leſt you ſhould looſe them by it, or your Antichriſtian ſpirit be diſcovered by them: for none can diſcover the <hi>Quakers</hi> cheat and deceit, but us the choſen Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Spirit, for your Doctrine is altogether Antichriſtian which doth deny both the Father and the Son to be in the form or perſon of a man in heaven above the ſtars, diſtinct of himſelf from Angels and man, and any other creature. And if you look but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> you may ſee what you are, for that is the fitteſt Book for <hi>Quakers</hi> to look into, there I have had to do with ſuch like ſpirits are you are, who have gone in the ſame ſteps of deſpiſing and blaſpheming againſt the Doctrine of the true God declared by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, as you have; for you have moſt wickedly ſpoken evil of as pure Truths as ever was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or revealed by Prophet, or Apoſtle; for God hath choſen us by voice of words, as he did them, and hath given us the Spirit of Revelation and Interpretation, as he did them; and who ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth the Doctrine of us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, deſpiſeth him that ſent us, even Jeſus Chriſt the living God, who hath choſen us to pull down, and cut in ſunder ſuch Antichriſtian devil:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45752:9"/>
as you are, who owneth no other God but what is within you, which hath cauſed you to blaſpheme againſt the perſon of God without you, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus in glory; for thoſe Books of <hi>John Reeve's</hi> writing do own no other God but the Man Chriſt Jeſus in glory, who ſpake to him three mornings together to the hearing of the ear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you have called that Voice, <hi>A Dream;</hi> you have called that God or Chriſt, that could not make all things of nothing, <hi>A falſe Chriſt, a devil:</hi> you have called the Doctrine of the true God, <hi>A Lye, a Deceit, Error, Darkneſs, Blaſphemy,</hi> with many other wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed blaſphemous ſpeeches in the Margent of the Book, too tedious to relate; Therefore for theſe your wicked Blaſphemies againſt the holy Spirit of Chriſt that ſent, and revealed thoſe Doctrines unto us, I do pronounce <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> Quaker, curſed and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both in ſoul and body, from the preſence of God, elect men and Angels to eternity: neither ſhall the Light within you, nor Infinite Spirit, which you call God without you, deliver you from that Curſe I have pronounced upon you; but you ſhall know that God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, hath given power unto his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Witneſſes to curſe you to eternity, deliver your ſelf from it if you can. And if you do but read <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> you may ſee others of your brethren who have walked in the ſame ſteps of blaſphemy as you have, and will have the ſame reward with you. That Book would have been as a Looking-glaſs for you to ſee what your Principles are in the root, and what will be the fruit of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written by <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> one of the two laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Witneſſes unto the High and Mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in glory, in Heaven above the Stars.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45752:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
